NYSUT Vice President's office files. 6174/002
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Surveys. New York Teacher Readership Survey 12/12/97, 1997 (Box 29, Folder 3)
  Hart Research Report on Findings from Focus Groups Conducted for the American Federation of Teachers, December 1997; Hart Research Key Findings from a National Membership Survey Conducted for the American Federation of Teachers, October 1991; confidential questions, "A Nationwide Survey among Members of the AFT," October 1991; AFT report, "Valuable Views: A public opinion research report on the views of AFT teachers on professional issues," n.d., c. 1994; questions used in survey of AFT teachers, April 15-1-9, 1994
- Surveys. New York Teacher Readership Survey 1989-1990 (Box 29, Folder 4)
  "A Study of the UFT Bulletin and New York Teacher," conducted by Clark, Martire & Bartolomeo, Inc., February 1990; memos from competing research firms proposing research designs for survey; memo to Cortese summarizing and comparing proposals, May 22, 1989
- Surveys. New Member Survey 1994-1995 (Box 29, Folder 5)
  "Statewide Report on the NYSUT Survey of New Members, 1994-95"; survey questions; Commack Teachers Association comments on new teacher program, May 1995; related memos
- T.E.A.C.H.. See: Project T.E.A.C.H.
- TIMSS. See Third International Math and Science Study AFT Conference
- Take Our Daughters to Work 1995 (Box 29, Folder 6)
  Printed folder of materials by the Ms. Foundation for Women, including reader's companion to the Mother-Daughter Revolution, class activities for girls and boys, description of foundation; editorial defending exclusivity of event; NYSUT memo re event and agenda for activities
- Take Our Daughters to Work 4/23/96, 1996 (Box 29, Folder 7)
  NYSUT memo re event and agenda for activities
- Task Force. See under subject area
- TEACH. See: Project T.E.A.C.H.
- Teacher Aides. See: Teaching Assistants/Teacher Aides; see: Paraprofessionals; see: School-Related Personnel
- Teacher Center Conference 1988 (Box 29, Folder 8)
  Agenda, NYS Teacher Resource & Computer Training Centers 1988 Summer Institute; compilation of professional readers; list of participants; list of group consensus points
- Teacher Centers Ad Hoc Committee 1988 (Box 29, Folder 9)
  Memo from Cortese re report of NYSUT Task Force on Educational Policy re Teacher Centers; confidential memo, "Additional Information Regarding Local Control of Teacher Centers. Consortia Centers"; minutes of July 7 meeting; correspondence
- Teacher Centers Ad Hoc Committee 1986-1987 (Box 29, Folder 10)
  Meeting minutes, November 23, 1987; NYSUT policy background on teacher centers; Federal Register publication of Teacher Centers Program grant requirements, Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, January 11, 1978, and December 8, 1980; draft bylaws for the operation of teacher resource and computer training centers, August 1986; revised draft, Roles and Responsibilities of Teacher Resource and Computer Training Centers and Cooperating Local Education Agencies, July 3, 1986; State Education Department memo re application materials for program 1987-88
- Teacher Centers (folder 1 of 2) 1987 (Box 29, Folder 11)
  Memo to Cortese re desired changes in law re teacher centers, Feb. 6, 1987; Report by the Commissioner of Education to the Governor and Legislature on the New York State Teacher Resource and Computer Training Center Program, March 1987
- Teacher Centers (folder 2 of 2) 1987 (Box 29, Folder 12)
- Teacher Center Policy Board Meeting April 9, 1987 (Box 29, Folder 13)
  State Education Department Teacher Resource and Computer Training Centers 1986-87 Directory; teacher center analysis statistics; handwritten notes
- Teacher Center Training 1987 (Box 29, Folder 14)
  Memo re representation and hiring issues, July 14; memos re training, May
- Teacher Center. Middletown 1987 (Box 29, Folder 15)
  Memos re Labor Department decision about Middletown Teacher Center
- Teacher Compensation (folder 1 of 2) 1995 (Box 29, Folder 16)
  Consortium for Policy Research in Education agenda for conference series on teacher compensation, June 7-9, 1995; overviews of performance-based pay schemes in districts around the country; research paper by Linda Darling-Hammond, "Beyond Bureaucracy: Restructuring Schools for 'High Performance', 1995; "New Ideas for Reinventing Teacher Compensation," by Carolyn Kelley and Allan Odden, June 1, 1995; "Motivation for School Reform," Susan Albers Mohrman and Edward E. Lawler III, May 1995; draft, "Picking Winners: Recognition and Reward Programs for Public Schools," Charles T. Clotfelter, Duke University, and Helen F. Ladd, Brookings Institution, April 1995; related papers. See also: Pay for Performance; See also: Women's Issues. Comparable Worth
- Teacher Compensation (folder 2 of 2) 1994-1995 (Box 29, Folder 17)
- Teacher Compensation. Alternative Compensation Task Force Meeting (UFT) September 21-22, 2000 (Box 29, Folder 18)
  Packet of materials including agenda, research/policy papers, newspaper articles, draft resolution
- Teacher Compensation. Salaries 1990-1998 (Box 29, Folder 19)
  NYSUT booklet, "Dollars and Sense: Responding to Attacks on Teachers' Salaries: A Guide for Local Leaders"
- Teacher Compensation. AFT Consortium for Policy Research in Education. Teacher Pay System 11/2-4/94, 1994 (Box 29, Folder 20)
  Correspondence; Annotated Bibliography: School Organization and Compensation; draft paper, "History of Teacher Pay and Incentive Reforms," by Jean Protsik, Consortium on Policy Research in Education, University of Wisconsin. Madison, prepared for Conference on Teacher Compensation, November 2-4, 1994; related papers; list of invitees; prospectus: CPRE Project on Teacher Compensation, with cover letter from Albert Shanker to Antonia Cortese urging her to participate, September 7, 1994; invitation from CPRE
- Teacher Education 1991-2002 (Box 29, Folder 21)
  Draft of speech by AFT president Sandra Feldman at White House Conference on Preparing Quality Teachers, March 5, 2002; proposed changes to Commissioner's Regulations re teacher preparation; Metropolitan Life Survey of the American Teacher 1991: The First Year: New Teachers' Expectations and Ideals; background paper prepared for the National Commission on Teaching and America's Future, "The Current Status of Teaching and Teacher Development in the United States," by Linda Darling-Hammond, November 1994; summary report, "What Matters Most: Teaching for America's Future," report of the National Commission on Teaching and America's Future, September 1996; National Council for Accreditation of Teacher Education (NCATE), "Standards Procedures & Policies for the Accreditation of Professional Education Units," 1997; "The Essential Profession: A National Survey of Public Attitudes toward Teaching, Educational Opportunity and School Reform," Recruiting New Teachers, Inc. (funded by Philip Morris Companies Inc.), 1998; handwritten notes. See also: Professional Development
- Teacher Education 1965-1995 (Box 29, Folder 22)
  Dissertation abstract, "A Historical Analysis of the Changes in the Method of Certifying Teachers in New York State," Vincent Gazzetta, SUNY Albany, May 1965; Recommendations of the Commissioner's Task Force on Teacher Education and Certification, April 1, 1977; newsletter, Holmes Group Forum, spring 1992; reports and scholarly articles, "Tomorrow's Teacher: A Report of the Holmes Group," 1986; executive summary of "A Nation Prepared: Teachers for the 21st Century," report of the (Carnegie) Task Force on Teaching as a Profession, May 1986; "A License to Teach: Building a Profession for 21st-Century Schools," Linda Darling-Hammond et al., 1995; remarks of Chancellor R. Carlos Carballada to the Teacher Education Conference Board, September 25, 1992; handwritten notes
- Teacher Education, AFT Task Force on 1999-2000 (Box 29, Folder 23)
  Resolution on Teacher Education and Teacher Quality; press release, "AFT Calls for More Sweeping Changes in Teacher Training and More Rigorous Requirements for New Teachers," re report on teacher preparation, April 7, 2000; draft report for AFT K-16 Teacher Education Task Force, "Building a Profession: Strengthening Teacher Preparation," September 1999; revised report, "Building a Profession: Strengthening Teacher Preparation and Induction"
- Teacher Education, AFT Task Force on 1986-1999 (Box 29, Folder 24)
  Article reprints; press releases re survey of former teachers, 1986
- Teacher Education, AFT Task Force on 2/24/99, 1999 (Box 29, Folder 25)
  Agenda; draft report of task force, "Teacher Preparation: The Clinical Experience," February 17, 1999; draft background paper, "Entry/Exit Standards for Teacher Education"; related articles
- Teacher Education, AFT Task Force on 5/19/99 (Box 29, Folder 26)
  Meeting agenda and background materials; speech by AFT president Sandra Feldman, "Shaping Our Future: Teacher Preparation As Seem by Practicing Teachers," AACTE Conference, February 26, 1999; draft report of Teacher Education Task Force, "Teacher Preparation: The Core Curriculum," May 19, 1999; second draft: "Teacher Preparation: The Clinical Experience," May 19, 1999
- Teacher Education, AFT Task Force on (K-16) 7/10/99, 1999 (Box 29, Folder 27)
  Notice of meeting; "To Touch the Future: Transforming the Way Teachers Are Taught: An Action Agenda for College and University Presidents: Report of the President's Task Force on Teacher Education, American Council on Education"; newsletter of the Education Trust, Thinking K-16, featuring cover story, "Not Good Enough: A Content Analysis of Teacher Licensing Examination," spring 1999; U.S. Department of Education Draft Manual: Data System for Accountability Provisions of the Higher Education Amendments of 1998, Title II, July 20, 1999
- Teacher Education, AFT Task Force on 9/24/98, 1998 (Box 30, Folder 1)
  Agenda; AFT press release calling for end to emergency credentials for teachers; memo outlining questions to address in survey/background report
- Teacher Education, AFT Task Force on (folder 1 of 2) 5/13/98, 1998 (Box 30, Folder 2)
  Meeting agenda; handwritten notes; background papers
- Teacher Education, AFT Task Force on (folder 2 of 2) 5/13/98, 1998 (Box 30, Folder 3)
  Background materials for first meeting
- AFT Teacher Education & Teacher Quality 2000 (Box 30, Folder 4)
  "Building a Profession: Strengthening Teacher Preparation and Induction: Report of the K-16 Teacher Education Task Force"
- AFT Teacher Education & Teacher Quality. AFT/NYSUT Grant Meeting 9/27/00, 2000 (Box 30, Folder 5)
  Text of resolution, "Teacher Education and Teacher Quality"; handwritten notes
- Teacher Education Conference Board (TECB) Miscellaneous 1995-1996 (Box 30, Folder 6)
  Memo, "History and Background of the Teacher Education Conference Board," n.d.; constitution of the NYS Teacher Education Conference Board, with proposed changes; list of members
- Teacher Education Conference Board (TECB) Labels, 1993-1996 (Box 30, Folder 7)
  List of Council of University Deans; carbon copies of postage expenditures
- Teacher Education Conference Board 1991 (Box 30, Folder 8)
  Agenda, October 11, 1991, meeting; minutes of May 15, 1991, annual meeting; treasurer's report
- Teacher Education Conference Board Meeting (folder 1 of 2) 1988 (Box 30, Folder 9)
  Constitution of NYS Teacher Education Conference Board; agenda for September 30, 1988, meeting; minutes of TECB Executive Committee meeting, May 5, 1988; treasurer's report; membership list; minutes of annual meeting of May 5-6, 1988; profile of teacher job seekers and public school teachers, September 22, 1988; materials distributed at Board of Regents meeting, September 20, 1988; NYS School Boards Association response to the recommendations of the Task Force on the Teaching Profession, September 30, 1988; letter from NYSUT president Hobart to Cortese confirming her appointment as chair of TECB, September 21, 1988; newspaper clippings. See also: Education Reform. Post-Secondary. Revisions to Regulations May 1980
- Teacher Education Conference Board Meeting (folder 2 of 2) 1988 (Box 30, Folder 10)
  "The Report that Fails: A Response to the NYPIRG Analysis of the NTE [National Teachers Examination] in New York," Educational Testing Service, 1988; ETS paper, "The National Teacher Exams Pass"; Educational Priorities Panel report, "Teachers for the Apple: Why New York City Can't Staff Its Schools," November 1987; State Education Department proposed amendment re teacher certification, February 11, 1988; summary press release re report of the Commissioner's Task Force on the Teaching Profession, April 4, 1988
- Teacher Education Conference Board. Bilingual Education 1981-1990 (Box 30, Folder 11)
  Pamphlet, "Why Bilingual Education?" 1985; agenda; article reprints, "Bilingual Miseducation," Commentary, February 1990; commissioner's regulations, bilingual and English as a Second Language; related materials
- Teacher Education Conference Board. Meeting Dec. 14, 1990 (Box 30, Folder 12)
  Agenda; description of Kenmore Teacher Mentor Program; booklet, Model for Teacher Evaluation, Syracuse City School District, revised September 1, 1990; monograph, "A Guide to the Process of Evaluating School Principals," Connecticut Principals' Academy; correspondence; related materials; treasurer's report, September 24, 1990
- Teacher Education Conference Board. Meeting Dec. 7, 1989 (Box 30, Folder 13)
  Working paper by Educational Testing Service, "New Generation of Teacher Assessments," September 1989; handwritten notes
- Teacher Education Conference Board. Meeting Oct. 19, 1989 (Box 30, Folder 14)
  Agenda for Productivity Forum 1989 fall roundtable, "New Roles for Managers"; related correspondence
- Teacher Education Conference Board. Meeting May 5, 1989 (Box 30, Folder 15)
- Teacher Education Conference Board. Meeting Feb. 16-17, 1989 (Box 30, Folder 16)
  State Education Department Commissioner's draft proposal on teaching as a profession
- Teacher Education Conference Board. Meeting Dec. 9, 1988 (Box 30, Folder 17)
  Summary minutes of October 24 meeting
- Teacher Education Conference Board. Annual Meeting May 5-6, 1988 (Box 30, Folder 18)
  Agenda; minutes of February 26 meeting; printed report, spring 1988; budget for 1987-88; handwritten notes
- Teacher Education Conference Board. Meeting Feb. 26, 1988 (Box 30, Folder 19)
  Agenda; minutes of December 11, 1987, meeting; treasurer's report, related materials
- Teacher Education Conference Board. Meeting Dec. 11, 1987 (Box 30, Folder 20)
  Stated education Department press release, "Commissioner Sobol Appoints Four Task Forces," September 18, 1987; proposed agenda; executive committee minutes of September 28
- TECB File Cases in Storage 1978-1987 (Box 30, Folder 21)
  Handwritten notes about files in storage
- Teacher Evaluation 1984-1998 (Box 30, Folder 22)
  Excerpts from collective bargaining agreement between Board of Education and Manhasset Education Association, "Manhasset Public Schools Teacher Supervision and Evaluation Program," June 1998; Rand Corporation paper, "Taking the Measure of Excellence: The Case against Basing Teacher Evaluation on Student Test Scores," by Linda Darling-Hammond, fall 1984
- Teacher Evaluation. Tennessee (folder 1 of 2) 1983 (Box 30, Folder 23)
  Description of Tennessee Master Teacher Program, Tennessee Department of Education, January 1983; draft outline of proposed evaluation system; related documents
- Teacher Evaluation. Tennessee (folder 2 of 2) 1983 (Box 30, Folder 24)
  Evaluation instruments for competency certification; candidate questionnaire
- Teacher Liability 1996 (Box 30, Folder 25)
  Memo to Cortese from NYSUT general counsel's office discussing liability of teachers during school- sponsored trips and other activities, obligation of school districts to pay for legal defense, under Education Law, December 16, 1996
- AFT Teacher Quality Report Meeting 1/19/00, 2000 (Box 30, Folder 26)
  Agenda of Teacher Quality Report Advisory meeting; drafts of resolution on teacher education and teacher quality; related memos
- Teacher Quality 1997-1998 (Box 30, Folder 27)
  Results of survey of voters in NYS by Peter D. Hart Research, May 5, 1997; graphical presentations of results of voter survey and survey of AFT members re teacher quality, April 5-9, 1997; preliminary copy of "The Essential Profession: A Survey of Public Attitudes in California toward Teaching, Educational Opportunity and School Reform," Recruiting New Teachers, Inc., 1998; statement on the union role in assuring teacher quality, presented by Educational Issues Committee to AFT Executive Council, n.d.
- Teacher Quality, AFT/NEA Conference on 9/25-27/1998 (Box 30, Folder 28)
  Handbook, "Peer Assistance & Peer Review," prepared for Shaping the Profession That Shapes the Future conference; correspondence
- Teacher Supplies (Out of Pocket), 1992-1996 (Box 30, Folder 29)
  NYSUT press release, "Teachers Dip into Their Own Pockets to Pay for Supplies," re findings of statewide survey, March 20, 1992, with notation for average in 1996
- Teacher Unions & Student Performance 1996 (Box 30, Folder 30)
  Study by Institute for Wisconsin's Future, "Are Teacher Unions Hurting American Education? A State-by-State Analysis of the Impact of Collective Bargaining among Teachers on Student Performance," October 1996; review of study by NYSUT associate Patrick Flynn. See also: Student Acheivement. Urban High Schools
- Teacher of the Year. Selection Committee 2000-2005 (Box 30, Folder 31)
  Calls for nominations, with description of criteria and process, 2000-2005; letter of congratulations from NYSUT president Tom Hobart to selected teacher Elizabeth Day, Mechanicville Teachers Association, December 7, 2004; correspondence with members of Selection Committee; some correspondence from 1965-66
- Teacher of the Year Luncheon 6/16/03, 2003 (Box 30, Folder 32)
  Invitation; nomination forms
- Teacher of the Year 6/17/02, 2002 (Box 30, Folder 33)
- Teacher of the Year. Regents Meeting 6/11-12/01, 2001 (Box 30, Folder 34)
  Invitation from State Education Department
- NYSUT Ad Hoc Task Force on Regents Task Force on Teaching Recommendations 12/3/98, 1998 (Box 30, Folder 35)
  List of members of ad hoc task force; memo from Cortese announcing next meeting; draft Interim NYSUT Policy Regarding SED's Annual Professional Performance Review and District Professional Development Plan, November 24, 1998
- NYSUT Ad Hoc Task Force on Regents Task Force on Teaching Recommendations 10/19/98 (Box 30, Folder 36)
  Meeting agenda; NYSUT questions
- NYSUT Ad Hoc Task Force on Regents Task Force on Teaching August-September 1998 (Box 30, Folder 37)
  List of members of ad hoc task force; memo from Cortese announcing first meeting of ad hoc task force to respond to Regents task force recommendations; memo to Regents from Regents task force, amending report
- Regents Task Force on Teaching 1998 (Box 30, Folder 38)
  Report; amendments to report; NYSUT talking points re report, and disputed issues; NYSUT press release, "Statement by NYSUT First Vice President Antonia Cortese on Regents Task Force on Teaching Report," July 15, 1998. See also: Professional Development
- Regents Task Force on Teaching 1996-1998 (Box 30, Folder 39)
  Regents' charge to task force, 1996; chronology of key issues; UFT Professional Studies Program Questions and Answers; NYC Board of Education Professional Studies Program Catalogue, Spring/Summer 1997; New York Times article re Regents, teacher standards, July 15, 1998
- Regents Task Force on Teaching 1997-1998 (Box 30, Folder 40)
  Response of NYSUT and NEA/NY to the Selected Positions of the Regents Task Force on Teaching: Report Dated September 17, 1997, with cover letter to Regents, November 12, 1997; confidential draft of task force paper, "Teaching to Higher Standards: New York's Commitment," April 14, 1998; NYSUT memo commenting on draft, March 5, 1998; State Education Department draft, "Edited Excerpts of Oral and Written Comments on the Proposals in the Task Force Paper of November 14, 1997," February 6, 1998; testimony by Cortese at Regents Task Force on Teaching Forum, December 9, 1997; Regents discussion item re task force issues, December 12, 1997; "short version," Teachers for Tomorrow: Report of the Regents' Task Force on Teachin [sic], November 1997
- Regents Task Force on Teaching. 1997 (Box 30, Folder 41)
  "Teachers for Tomorrow," report of the Regents Task Force on Teaching, November 1997; NYSUT Summary and Talking Points on Selected Recommendations of the Regents' Task Force on Teaching Report (November 7, 1997), prepared for NYSUT Board of Directors, November 20-21, 1997; related materials
- Regents Task Force on Teaching, Part I. Overview 1997 (Box 30, Folder 42)
  Presentation points
- Regents Task Force on Teaching. Meeting with Randi Weingarten, UFT 12/16/97, 1997 (Box 30, Folder 43)
  Confidential notes, Meeting on Regents Task Force on Teaching at UFT, 12/1/97; Principles for Charter School Legislation in New York State; overview of Charter School Bill # 325; draft, the Teacher Quality Act of 1998, January 5, 1998; handwritten notes
- Regents Task Force on Teaching (Contract Language) 1997 (Box 30, Folder 44)
  Rochester City School District Career in Teaching Joint Governing Panel, "PART [Performance Appraisal Review for Teachers] and Summative Appraisal Guidebook," 1996; materials from Williamsville Teachers' Association re use of extra professional days, June 9, 1997; materials from Kenmore Teachers Association re staff development, July 25, 1997; Memorandum of Understanding between the North Syracuse Central School District and the North Syracuse Education Association, September 1, 1996; memo to Cortese summarizing contract provisions in these districts, August 27, 1997
- Regents Task Force on Teaching. Public Forums, Albany HS 12/1/97, 1997 (Box 31, Folder 1)
  Report of the task force, "Teachers for Tomorrow," November 1997; condensed report, prepared for Regents, November 7, 1997; confidential notes of meeting, focusing on tenure, performance reviews, professional development, and internships; NYSUT summary and talking points on selected recommendations of the Regents' Task Force on Teaching (November 7, 1997), prepared for NYSUT Board of Directors; draft testimony by Cortese for Regents Task Force on Teaching forum, December 9, 1997
- Regents Task Force on Teaching. Forums, n.d. (Box 31, Folder 2)
  Handwritten notes from forum in Ithaca; questionnaire, "Survey of Opinion on the Regents Task Force on Teaching Report"
- Regents Task Force on Teaching. NYSUT Board of Directors Meeting 6/30/97, 1997 (Box 31, Folder 3)
  Agenda; draft Regents staff paper on teaching; minutes of May 1, 1997, NYSUT Board of Directors meeting
- Regents Task Force on Teaching (folder 1 of 2) 1997 (Box 31, Folder 4)
  Highlights of proposals of task force; proposal for a Professional Standards and Practices Board to replace Teacher Education, Certification, and Practices Board (TECAP)
- Regents Task Force on Teaching (folder 2 of 2) 1997 (Box 31, Folder 5)
- Regents Task Force on Teaching 1996-1997 (Box 31, Folder 6)